It's a place created by the paper
industry which thrived greatly until it
didn't.
>> No one could have anticipated this
happen.
>> The life was gone in the magic city.
>> You call it the magic city?
>> Yeah. Because it grew out of the woods.
>> We keep hoping there's going to be big
things on the other side of the gate
there.
>> Did you work in the mill back in the
day?
>> I did.
>> A lot better back then than it is now.
But
>> company owned all the real estate in
this town.
>> Pay was superb. They said, "Here's your
$300,000. Do with it what you want."
>> This is a funky place. The bear with the
bra.
>> This was a state-of-the-art paper
machine. I could feel this room just
vibrating.
>> It's almost like a bit of uh you're
living in a socialist world.
>> Yeah. The company wanted you to have a
place to recreate. You signed a 99-year
lease.
>> It feels like I'm in the 80s right now.
>> That's the joy of Milan.
Good morning, guys. Here we are going to
a town in northern Maine, deep in the
sticks. A place created by the paper
industry which thrived greatly until it
didn't. In 2008, it shut down, closed
its doors. Thousands of people left
town. Real estate plummeted. Things
changed. So, today we're meeting up with
the guy who actually flipped the switch
that one final time at the paper mill.
grew up here. This whole story is here
to get an inside look of what this far
corner of America is like. Let's do
this.
This is the mill deck.
>> Yep. This is Great on the Paper Company.
Primary entrance when anybody that was
going to work in the mill back in the
early 1900s came through. The doors over
there on that side. This is Little Italy
now that we are in. The housing here was
all close together because everybody
walked to work. As the mill was being
built, this whole thing was a big hill.
They dug this all out by hand with
horses and carts and shovels.
>> So, the Italians came over from 1898 to
1900, right? 1500 of them.
>> Yep.
>> And there were only 2,000 people in the
town at that time.
>> There wasn't even that many. I mean
there I think the Italians were the
first settlers in Milanaka because they
were building the mill.
>> And I was reading they had to pay the
fee to get over. They didn't have the
money to come over. So they had to pay
the paper company back.
>> Correct.
>> Did they pay in script in the beginning?
You know, script company money.
>> No,
>> they never did that.
>> No, you were paid dollar bill.
>> There was no real economic differences,
right? Everyone was sort of doing the
same.
>> Well, you had a snob hill.
>> Can we go there today?
>> Yeah.
>> Snob Hill. Okay. And
>> as you can see, this still the I don't
want to say the lower class, but they
don't have the pride in their place
anymore here. This house right here was
made in out of Great Northern Paper
Company boxes and stuff. The whole
building is made up of just chopped up
into little pieces. They kept adding on
as the family grew.
>> Okay,
>> so this is the end of Little Italy right
here. And you notice the piles of stuff
and everything. Nobody ever comes out
here. Everybody goes the other way.
>> So the jobs left in 2008. What did
everyone do for work?
>> They went to work elsewhere. You're
traveling. You're on the interstate to
go to Bangor, work in areas. I worked
construction after the mill closed. I
traveled all over the state. And you can
see people have said now here have
started taking pride in their houses and
making them look decent.
>> Did the company own all of this real
estate? The company owned all the real
estate in this town. If you wanted to
build a house here, the company would
come over. They would dig the hole for
you, okay?
>> They would have the forms to build the
foundation. You paid for the cement, but
the forms, the labor to put the forms
in, dig the foundation was done with
Great Northern Paper Company. Period.
>> So, how did people get these homes now?
How do they own them now?
>> Five companies in, they said, "Okay, you
own the land. Period. You have a house
there, you own it.
>> So when the company left
>> When the company left, it was deed over.
>> So you got families being raised here.
You got kids here now.
>> Oh yes. Kids are still going to school
here. And this is why Milan is so
special is you could raise your children
and you knew they could not get into
trouble because if they did, the word in
the mill, hey, I saw your son run a
stoplight.
You were you were caught. Plain and
simple,
>> right? Everyone was looking out for
everyone.
>> Everyone was looking out for everybody
else. Now we are physically in the mill
property. Now
>> you still get access here. Not too many
guys have this gate control, do they?
>> No.
>> The lake that you see here on the right
is Ferguson Pond. Ferguson was the
architect engineer that built Great
Northern Paper Company. So this waterway
was named after him.
>> So Maine, I don't know if it still is.
It's known for paper lumber.
>> Is it still happening here in the state?
>> Yes. Madawaska has a paper company
that's split between United States and
Canada. They are subsidized by the
Canadian government to a point. It's
still operating. We suffered the
consequence of being by ourselves. It
took the life out of everybody in town
when the murder happened.
>> You remember that exact moment when they
told you guys?
>> Oh yeah. Oh yeah.
>> What was that like?
>> We couldn't believe it because we were
told if we were showed a profit for two
months, they would keep us operating. We
busted our tails to keep it operating
and make it profit. Well, we showed a
profit both months and our second month
was a really good profit. And then in
September they said you're done.
>> You're shut down.
>> What was the reasoning?
>> None.
>> Nothing.
>> Corporate said that they they didn't
feel that we could sustain that
profitability.
>> I think one of the biggest reasons at
the end of it Frasier paper which is
Madawasa was overseeing our operation as
well.
>> Okay.
>> So we were competing in the press rooms
>> and Madawaska is a couple hours north of
here.
>> Yeah, that is correct. We beat out
Madawaska hands down. We could make
better paper than them and make a
profit. That's the only logical reason
we could think of that would shut us
down and keep us down.
>> So you'd come in here back and it's
musty smelling. So if that bothers you,
we come head right back out.
>> Back in the in the day, we came through
over here. Your time clock was right
here and you went out that door to the
mill to go to work. This area over here
was a sitting area. They used to have a
fireplace going and the workers would
get here early. They would just all
congregate in that area and wait for the
time clock to reach time and punch a
card and off you went and went to work.
>> It was just 8 to 5 or 9 to 5.
>> No. uh 8 8 to 4 4 to 12 and 12 to 8
shifts.
>> Never stopped.
>> 24/7 never stopped. You're standing in a
place that from 1900 on
workers came through here to make paper.
>> Good memories doing that here.
>> All absolutely absolutely great memories
doing that here.
>> Does it feel sad seeing it like this now
or just
>> It does. This is the part that really
hurts. You look at this wall and you you
say, "My father could have touched this
wall. My grandfather could have touched
this wall." That's the part that you
say, "I wanted my children to be able to
touch this wall."
>> Mhm.
>> And it it'll never happen anymore
because it's gone. Our Kataden is
working it trying to get the building
get this whole site back to a spot of
operation of some sort.
>> What? Kataden. What is that?
>> AA Kataden is just an organization that
purchased the mill as a nonprofit
>> and they want to renovate this mill,
make it useful again for what?
>> Don't know yet. whatever will will come
in and work here. Any industry that we
can get in here.
>> So, you guys all understood each other
well here because you're all on the same
journey.
>> Correct.
>> I'm sure there was infighting with
people. Some people didn't get along,
but
>> there was bantering.
>> Bantering.
>> I don't want to say infighting cuz you
had a passion for something. You did it
a certain way and everybody else had a
passion for something.
>> I mean, until the end, until the rug was
pulled out from you guys, did it feel
like a very stable life?
>> Oh, absolutely. like you knew what was
happening.
>> You knew you could retire here.
>> Okay.
>> And when you retired, you could live the
rest of your life in this community.
Talking about the good old days. The
life was gone in the magic city.
>> You call it the magic city.
>> Yeah. Because it grew out of the woods.
Everybody had something to do in
Milanet. And you lived here until you
passed away and then you went over on
the in the cemetery. All my ancestors
are right there.
So that's the beauty of this small town
is we are a family. Unfortunately, I
think that it has become a point where
now we're losing that family connection.
You don't know necessarily know who your
neighbors are. When I sit on my front
porch and watch the traffic go by, I
don't know who that guy was. So, I don't
know who that was. I
>> Who's moving in?
>> That's the point.
>> But why are people moving here? There's
no There's no work.
>> They're not moving here. They're
recreating here.
>> Oh, okay. So, Kataden Kataden is your
biggest mountain in Maine, right?
Correct. Up the road.
>> Yes. So, people recreate here. It's
becoming a recreation a tourism point.
>> How was the pay here?
>> Pay was superb.
>> Your wife was what?
>> She was trained as a teacher. She
graduated from college. Her first
teaching job was down on the coast
because the state would pay off your
education loan if you worked in a
depressed area for a period of time
>> and the coast was depressed.
>> The coast was depressed at that time.
>> Oh, interesting.
>> So, she worked there for 2 years, paid
off her student loans and then she got
her job in Milanino, which was one of
the highest paid teaching positions in
the state of Maine at the time. Is that
because the paper company was adding to
the salary or why?
>> The paper company was the majority
taxpayer and they didn't hesitate if the
school needed something. Yeah. We'll
we'll supply it. You know, uh you need
help with that. Okay. We'll send the
workers over to help you with your
boiler or with the with an issue you had
at the school.
>> So, at the time, you'd want to be a
teacher here versus Portland or a
coastal town,
>> right? That's interesting.
>> This is number 11 paper machine right
here. This was a state-of-the-art paper
machine. Machine
ran at 3800
ft per minute,
300 in wide, 24/7.
I don't know how this one will work for
me, but for you, just put it on your
head.
>> Okay.
>> And push the on button right there.
Okay.
>> It'll give you light.
>> And you just put that on the front.
>> Yep. Yeah. Just put on your head like a
like a headband. Yep. That'll that'll
light up light your way.
Okay.
So,
>> Oh, this is Holy M.
>> This is huge. Yeah. I can feel this room
just vibrating with that machine
running.
>> And so, we're talking like computer
paper, 8 by11 paper.
>> Well, no. What this machine here made
was super calendared agrade paper. So,
what when you see something like that,
well, walk around it, okay?
>> But I can't guarantee what it's going to
be like. So, that machine started way
down on the other end.
Basically, if you followed this wall all
the way down where that wall stopped on
there, that was the start of this
machine. Overhead cranes here were 50
ton cranes. Couldn't pick up a roll of
paper if you let it go too big. You're
talking about a a roll of paper that was
over 50 tons.
And then that would roll off and that
would roll roll down the rails to the
winder and then they would cut it up
into smaller rolls for the whatever the
customer wanted. If you could wave your
magic wand, do you wish you could bring
it all back
>> in a heartbeat? In a heartbeat. This was
my life.
Nothing on this machine I had I don't
think I hadn't touched.
everywhere. This machine when we had a
shutdown,
I planned the shutdown. I would probably
put 10 miles a day walking around this
machine on a shutdown day. Just walking
around the machine, checking on the
crews, checking on the progress because
the machine wasn't making paper, you
were losing money. If it was a 12-hour
shutdown, I was here for 24 hours.
>> You loved your job.
>> I loved my job. I love the people I
worked with. That was the the job is a
job. The people make the job. That's the
big thing. And this family of people
that were here. Uh this there was a
control room right here. And one of the
fellas that used to sit in this control
room was a good friend of mine. He just
passed away, but I still can see him
sitting there. And one day, one day when
he was he called me in at 3:00 in the
morning, you got to get in here.
And I did. I I no question. Got up and I
came. I got the problem solved. He said
right there. I looked up and there's my
name and my telephone number. He said,
"If this thing even coughs,
that number is going on."
And I said, "Not a problem, Keith." I
said Keith Bopane was his name. Great
guy. Little rough, a little gruff, but
he would help you in a heartbeat.
That's the way these people were. We
were all a family of brothers and
sisters that worked together. Had one
goal in mind. Get paper off that
machine.
>> Dick, I got a paper story for you. Okay.
>> My book just went live.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> Published a book.
>> Did you?
>> So, did paper that's in my book come
from a place like this?
>> Chances are the paper that is printing
your book was engineered in Milwaukee.
>> Come on.
>> No. It was designed in and engineered in
Milanocket, Maine to create that
condition for that style of paper.
That's one of the things that they did
here was Great Northern was the largest
paper company in the United States at
one time. We had our own research
department, pulp and paper engineers
that were designing grades of paper for
different things like a book, a
magazine, a newspaper, the makeup of
that piece of paper that's in your book.
>> Okay. the type of wood that they used,
all of that is a part of that.
>> All right, so for all of you guys, the
book is now live. You can buy online,
Barnes & Noble, Amazon,
>> and there's a little bit of the
Milaninoet story in that book.
>> Correct.
>> QR scan here or link down below. Your
fellow Americans, that's what it's
called, Dick.
>> Yeah.
>> It's about all of us.
>> Okay.
>> Cool stories across this great country.
Y
>> it's so big. This is why I have almost
an endless amount of work. It's so big I
can keep discovering.
>> Right.
>> And this part of Maine I knew nothing
about.
>> Yeah. So this here is over the tracks.
Okay. This is where as the mill grew and
needed more workers. They kept building
houses. Well, they ran out of space down
in the valley. So they started coming up
on the other side of the tracks.
>> Did it stay mostly Italian or you guys
started immigrating from all over?
>> This was all over. Now, once the mill
came into operation, this now became all
over.
>> It feels like I'm in the 80s right now.
>> And I mean this in a good way.
>> It's just simple living. It feels like
>> that's the joy of Milanet.
>> Yeah.
>> Very quaint, calm, know your neighbors.
You know what's going on. You do your
best to say hi to the person walking by.
When you walk out and you'll see your
neighbor struggling, you don't just walk
by with your nose in the air. You stop
and help them. That's what makes this
community so great.
>> Yeah. It feels like grandma's baking an
apple pie right now as we speak.
>> Right. Doesn't it have that feel?
>> Yeah.
>> Some vanilla ice cream.
>> This is the oldest church in Milanaka.
This church was built before that high
school was built.
>> Oh, look at that beauty.
>> That's where I graduated.
>> Oh, that is cool. Still functioning? No,
it's a assisted living building now.
>> So that was part of the strategy with
the company town, right? Make it really
nice so people wanted to stay.
>> Yep.
>> Is this the legendary snob hill?
>> Snob Hill. The high society lived up
here. The doctors, the lawyers. This was
the old Catholic school right here. Now
turned into a lowincome apartment.
>> So these people are moving into these
places from out of town or
>> some are. This is the old nuns home,
which is now a thrift store.
>> Look at that block glass. I love that
style. Okay, so these are the high
rollers back in the day.
>> Yep. We all went go trick-or-treating in
Snob Hill because that's where the
biggest amount of candy was.
>> So they got bigger lots.
>> Yeah, they had bigger lots. They had
bigger houses.
>> This one's for sale.
>> Yep.
>> What do you think? How much?
>> I'd be willing to bet you it's going to
be right around a half a million.
>> No way.
>> Yeah. Look, this one here is for sale.
It just shows you that you can go in
some areas of the town and it's
operating, but then you go other areas
of the town.
>> This house here was bought. Look at it's
turned into a shack house. You go down
two houses down and you got a beautiful
house. Dr. Mason was a surgeon brought
here by great paper company.
>> Was everyone like you so fired up on the
company?
>> No. My father instilled in us that you
need to have a positive attitude
whatever you do and you never want to
look at it from strictly your view
because your view can be tainted. So you
got to look at the view from your side
other people's side and then make an
educated decision on to what's best for
the community and for for society.
>> What would be the argument against the
paper company? What would people
complain about?
>> Noise.
>> Okay. Yeah. Sure.
>> Smell.
>> Air quality had to be bad, huh?
>> No, it wasn't bad. This was not a craft
mill. The gases that you used could
create a smell. We would create a smell,
but the cooking process to cook the
chips would create a smell. Yes.
>> Officially off Snob Hill back in the
valley.
>> Yep. Now we're going to go down Main
Street. When we were kids, when I first
got my driver's license, we just drive
make the loop. And the loop was drive
down Main Street, see what action was
going on, and then up Kataden Avenue,
back down Main Street.
>> Coming out here, I thought it was going
to be a little more rundown to be
honest.
>> Like a rust belt town type feel.
>> Not necessarily.
>> There's a little bit of it, but
>> it's a little bit of it. And it started
I mean, see like there's that place
there. I mean, it's spotty.
>> It's spotty. There you go. Right. And
then you have this place right here.
>> Right. They take care of their place.
>> How to build community. Turn off your
TV. Leave your house.
>> Yeah.
>> Know your neighbors. Look up when you're
walking. Greet people. Sit on your
stoop. Plant flowers. Use your library.
>> Yep.
>> This is cute. It's nice.
>> It's a quaint little town.
>> It's had to come back with tourism. You
see Yum Bake Shop.
>> The Appalachin Trail Cafe.
>> That has been here all along.
>> Okay. That's been here the whole time.
>> Changed the names a couple times.
>> It's spotty. Milanaka insurance agencies
had better days.
>> This one here was another insurance
agency closed.
>> Okay. Insurance is not doing well here,
huh? Got some vacancy. Snack bar.
>> This gray building right here is
probably the next one on the chopping
block of being demoed. They've let it go
so bad now that it's not worth fixing.
>> Oh yeah.
>> That used to be a coffee shop right
there. We all went and get our coffee.
That used to be a pharmacy.
>> Okay. So, quite a few vacancies actually
once you start cruising it.
>> This one here is just being renovated.
They had some community development
block grants for facade work
>> like this one here was all redone
>> from the state or from the feds?
>> Well, it came from the state and there
used to be a bowling alley there, but it
collapsed. They stopped using it and uh
the guy that bought it never heated it
and collapsed.
>> So, it's sort of just in flux right now.
>> Yeah. Then
>> are you filling up this school? It seems
like a pretty big school for out here.
>> When I graduated, there was 356.
>> Okay.
>> If I recall, in my class, the class that
graduated this year, I think there was
35.
>> Oh, that's it.
>> That's it. It just shows you the
comparison between back in the heyday
and now.
>> So, for the kids, this is the place in
the summer, right?
>> Yep. That's pool. That's the new pool.
>> Home of the Minutemen. Home of the
Minutemen.
>> So, if you have a 35 student graduating
class, Yeah.
>> your sports teams aren't really
happening, are they?
>> We took the state championship this year
in football.
>> Come on.
>> Yeah.
>> No way.
>> Yep.
>> Why?
>> Because from the little age, little pro,
right on up through ingrained in
football. Their parents get involved in
football.
>> The Minutemen won state champs.
>> Yes, they did this year.
>> I mean, what did that do for town?
>> It's a big boost. The houses in town are
just houses. They're just a structure.
It's the people. The people are what
really makes the difference. And if you
have people that care about each other,
then you have a great community to live
in.
>> And here you can just let your kids go
wherever and do whatever.
>> It's like four-wheeler down the side of
the road. Nobody nobody stops and you
can go down Main Street with your
four-wheeler.
This is the new development.
>> The new as in when?
>> 1956.
>> Okay.
>> This was the new development and it
still has the name the new development.
>> So these were company houses.
>> Now these streets were all designed by
Great Northern Paper Company for the
employees. The employees wanted to build
the house. They found a lot. The company
would come up, bulldoze the opening for
the foundation, put the forms up for the
foundation, build the foundation, and
then you built your house on that
foundation.
>> You owned everything though, right?
>> You owned everything then.
>> Okay. By that time, by the 50s.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So, a bit bigger. You can just see
the evolution of homes in America,
right?
>> Correct. Correct. A whole different
environment here.
>> And these were massive at the time, but
now they look small. Right.
>> The frontage. Look at how much frontage
here. This is like that quintessential
50s lifestyle, right?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. But what are these people doing
for work right now? Cuz they look like
they're doing pretty well. Many of them.
>> Some are teachers. Some are construction
workers that travel to work.
>> They're tra Okay. They're traveling out
of town.
>> They travel out of town. It's their
family house. They grew up here.
>> Yep.
>> Their their parents passed away. They
got the house. They want to live here.
They want to raise their kids here, but
they have to work out of town. They'll
sacrifice because they want this.
>> This is called Cork Barrel Hill.
>> Why is that?
>> Because back when they were logging in
the early days, they had a wagon load of
supplies going into the camps and one of
them happened to be a barrel of pork and
uh the barrel of pork came off and
rolled all the way down the hill.
>> Seriously.
>> So pork barrel
>> stayed ever since.
>> Pork barrel hill. ATV trails are
phenomenal here.
>> Okay. So, just out in these woods here.
>> Yep. The snowmobile trails in the
wintertime are the best in the area. We
are now at the campsites area. This is
the dyke. Guess who built it?
>> Let me guess.
>> Great Northern Paper Company,
>> of course.
>> And the dyke holds the water on that
side.
>> Okay.
>> This is the same elevation as North Twin
Dam, which fed the wood to the mill.
>> Okay. Gotcha.
And now it's a bunch of camps.
>> Well, this has always been camps around
here.
>> Nice. Look at this. Oh, look at the
planes out there.
>> Yeah, there's a there's a flying
service.
>> So, you can fly in.
>> Full disclosure, I am a pilot.
>> You got a little plane here?
>> I I used to have a plane here. I sold
it.
>> Okay.
>> Cuz college educations were more
important.
>> And these are all little cabins out
here. Little camps.
>> Yep. We're going to go to my brother's
camp.
>> Oh, cool. Hopefully he's still here. And
this used to be the dyke store where
when we were kids, my grandfather had an
island over here. I had a camp on the
island. And we we used to drive, take
the boat, come down to the dock here, go
over and go to the ice house and get a
block of ice for the refrigerator.
So every day we'd have to come get a
block of ice.
>> And we And then we My grandfather would
say, "You want a candy bar?" Yep. Okay.
would go over to get a candy bar. This
is another place that has a lot of
special meaning to me.
>> And so you're in town, the weekend
comes. A lot of families have camps up
here.
>> Yep. I don't think Rod's here. I don't
see his vehicle.
>> Oh, this is cool.
>> Yeah, they're gone. So,
>> can we walk out there?
>> Yeah. Oh, yeah. Absolutely. The shades
are down. So,
>> how did he get it? Not you.
>> He married into it.
>> Okay. Her father had the camp and her
father when he passed away gave the camp
over to her.
>> It feels, this is going to sound wild, a
little bit like Finland.
>> Yeah.
>> It's got some Alaska to it. It's got a
little upper peninsula, Michigan.
>> It just feels far north. And so you just
sit back, do some fishing, do some
barbecuing.
>> That's that's what he's got the boat
for. Takes the boat out,
>> on the lake. and uh he'll take around
the lake and anchor out and just drop a
line and let it fish.
>> Yeah, this is really special out here.
>> He can he can do that. I can't. I have
no patience.
>> But yeah, this is their summer home. The
company wanted you to have a place to
recreate. They divided up the lots. You
signed a 99-year lease.
>> Really?
>> Then those lots were yours for 99 years.
It's almost like a bit of uh you're
living in a socialist world, would you
say?
>> Yeah. But then when Great Northern got
done, then they sold the lots. And I
know just a thought process. Yeah.
>> This lot right here,
>> I think he said they paid $40,000 just
for the land once the Great Northern
said to lease it because it was
waterfront property,
>> right? So he bought the land because he
didn't if you didn't buy the land, you
had to tear the camp down.
Okay.
>> Okay.
>> You were you were you were caught in a
choke point because of that reason.
>> It reminds me of Ukraine where my wife
is from.
>> Yeah.
>> They have dachos. So the country home.
>> Mhm.
>> And in Soviet times they lived in the
apartment blocks usually in the city and
then a lot of families had doas in the
countryside.
>> Yeah.
>> They grow their vegetables and
>> Right.
>> get away from it all.
>> And so was the company actually giving
these properties out to people? They
>> like how would you get one?
>> Yeah, you you'd have to go in if you if
you found a lot that didn't have a camp
on it, you would go into the company and
ask if you can get this lot and if you
work for the company, not a problem.
Yep. Sign the paperwork. 99ear lease. Go
>> 99year lease. I think that's is what go
build your And today because of the the
land use act, you can't you'd never be
able to build this close to the water.
>> Oh, right.
Yeah, guys, this is a special place.
Summertime.
So peaceful.
Take a listen.
Raj Camp is a very basic camp. They
wanted to keep it that way. That's his
homemade pizza oven. Oh, nice.
I found the stove and I said, "You want
that?" He said, "Oh, yeah." And then he
put a top on it. Makes homemade pizza.
>> All these camps are so cool.
>> They're all built basically with the
logs and stuff that they had here and
the stones,
>> right? So, you could make this for very
cheap.
>> These are the things that made
Milaninoet again so special.
>> I guess there's a bit of nostalgia.
Okay. I didn't live in this world.
>> I can get it through you a little bit
>> seeing you observe these places.
>> But I think what's attractive is just
the simplicity of it all
>> and the pre-technology
>> before the screens and it's just
>> simple things that I think most of us
long for,
>> right? It's the simple life.
>> The simple life.
>> Yeah.
>> Can you recreate it now or it's just the
time the simplicity is gone? Even now
it's gone. the cost cost is driven it
out.
>> You can't do it.
>> You can't do it. I mean,
>> yeah,
>> I say you can't. You still can, but you
really have to work at it. You have to
have that desire to say, "No, I'm going
to saw that log with a handsaw.
>> You have to be very disciplined."
>> Yes. That's what we're losing today is
that ability. My brother has that
ability. I have that ability to take
that tree and make something out of it.
But your kids left town.
>> But the kids all left town. They're all
computer geeks.
>> One's in Las Vegas.
>> Yeah. I've been taught them that desire
to do it yourself. Fix it yourself. They
do. But they have to have the modern
tools to do it.
>> I'm working all the time, so I'm hiring
someone.
>> Yeah.
>> That's just the reality.
>> Yeah. Exactly.
>> Things are always beautiful when looking
back through the lens of nostalgia,
right?
>> Yeah. I'm a realist in that sense. I
love the technology now. That makes life
so much easier in many ways.
>> And
>> but part of me does miss that old world.
And I think that's why I do these
videos.
>> When I was that age in the summertime,
I took the lawn mower and I went house
to house looking, can I mow your lawn?
>> I me the same. That's not happening at
all these days in Milanaka.
>> The little neighborhood kid knocking on
doors. Can I mow your lawn?
>> No.
>> Done.
gone. Those are the times that you were
taught to earn money. And if you earn
money, you could afford these things,
these toys or this,
>> right?
>> I enjoy this vehicle because I've earned
it.
>> Yep.
>> That's that that's that's the bottom
line. I've earned it.
>> If it was given to you, you wouldn't
enjoy it.
>> Exactly.
>> 100%.
>> Or you enjoy it for a day,
>> right? And I take care of it.
>> Do you get a pension from the company or
if it went bankrupt? There's no pension.
>> They divested their the pensions to the
employees. I had $300,000
of a pension. They said, "Okay, here's
your $300,000.
Do with it what you want." And I
invested it and I invested it wisely.
A lot of people took it and spent it.
>> You just invest in like what? S&P 500 or
something?
>> I Yeah, the NAS I'm I'm pretty heavy in
the NASDAQ. Okay.
>> But again, tech stocks cuz I I worked in
electronics in the mill. I said tech
stocks are the way way to put your money
to have it grow. And it's done. It's
done a great job for me. I'm financially
stable.
Therefore, I can afford this toy now.
This porch this year putting all the
windows in it. Well, thanks for bringing
me around.
>> Absolutely. This is my life.
>> Yeah. No,
>> it's it's tapping into a different
America and that's what I do. I try to
get in all different lifestyles and
places,
>> right?
>> This is a unique one.
>> Yeah. to have him grown up and and say
that you went to a one room schoolhouse
to being in charge of
a paper mill as far as the electrical
to being in a community that has no
industry other than tourism
which I don't necessarily am 100%
positive for because I don't think it
pays
the wages that industry does. I can't
say I want one or the other. You need
them both. People have to recreate.
But people have to earn a living, too.
You have to have a balance. If you don't
have that balance, you're going to have
just a community pass through where
people come to recreate and leave. and
the people that are here. It's all
lowpaying jobs. If you get the price up
too high, people aren't going to come.
It's as simple as that. So, you can't
pay what that manufacturing job paid.
>> Yeah, makes sense.
>> Dick, I'm going to go wander downtown
for a bit.
>> Y,
>> it's been an honor, a pleasure.
>> Absolutely.
>> Thanks for bringing us into your world.
>> You uh don't hesitate. your family now.
>> Ah, thank you.
>> So, so you come back, you know where to
you know where to shop.
>> All right, D. Thank you.
What's going on here in Milanet?
Lee Coach, excellence in all we do. Tea
Part Tea Party's making a comeback in
Milanino. Pokemon senior coffee chat.
It's cool to see it through Dick's eyes,
right? Like go back to those times that
weren't that long ago when everyone just
walked up the road here around that bend
where the paper mill was on the same
page cuz they're all sort of doing the
same thing, making similar money, very
safe, well connected. The camp, it
sounds quite amazing. Now, as a realist,
I know it's not my personality to go to
the mill every day and work in the
company town, but I totally get it. like
it totally makes sense the perceived
security, right? It was very secure
until it wasn't. But for those decades,
you know, when people worked there, they
didn't worry about I don't think I'm
sure some did, but losing their jobs or
being out in the streets or having to
leave town
are worrying about
education for their kids.
We have living innovations, but looks
like it's for sale. This place over here
had more active days for sure.
Yeah.
Well, I'm glad I met with Dick because
doesn't seem like there's anyone else in
town to meet with.
This looks like a business that's
active. Oh, here we go. Creable Oil
Company.
You guys have an oil business?
>> Yes.
>> How are things?
>> Good. Yeah,
>> they're happening.
>> Flowing.
>> Flowing. Literally.
>> Yes.
>> Oh, that's great.
>> This is the oldest company in Milan.
>> Right here.
>> Period.
>> 1901.
>> 1901. Did you guys grow up here?
>> I did.
>> Okay.
>> She did. From what year?
>> 40 44 years.
>> We've been here for 44 years. She has.
I've I've been here my whole life. I
know.
>> Are you as fired up as dick about the
company, the town? We are. We are. We
keep hoping that uh there's going to be
big things on the other side of the gate
there.
>> What are they projecting? What's going
to happen over there?
>> Supposedly a salmon farm, but
>> Oh, they didn't tell me that. Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> So, there's something in the making.
>> Yes.
>> That's cool. Okay.
>> There's always something in the making.
We're just hoping
>> Yeah.
>> someday it'll come to fruition.
>> Do you feel like the town can go one way
or the other? Right now,
>> it's gone the other.
>> What's that? Tourism.
>> We We've been in the tank.
>> In the tank.
It's only getting better. The tourism's
picked up great and
>> and a lot of a lot of people are working
really hard
>> to make it work to make something happen
here. So,
>> it's a totally different Maine than the
coast. I was at the coast this morning.
Different world.
>> Oh, yeah.
>> They're not as laid-back as we are up
here
>> cuz there's nothing to be stressed
about. It doesn't look like
>> Oh, no. You you make your living. You
put your nose to the grindstoneone for
as many hours a day as you can and
the rest is in the Lord's hands.
>> That's right.
>> Right. So good community still.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Oh yeah. Safe older folks. Older folks.
>> There's a lot of older folks.
>> The younger ones moving out.
>> They've gone.
>> Yeah.
>> They've gone. Some of them are coming
back and buying places, working
remotely. Uh they love the outdoors.
They want to be home.
>> So the workforce could be there.
>> I don't think you'll have a hard time
convincing them to come back.
>> Okay. So you just need one big industry
to come in to provide the jobs. And you
think,
>> "Yeah, we're optimistic."
>> You're optimistic. I love it.
>> Yeah.
Look at this old beauty. Look at the
story. The men cutting the trees down,
dragging them away with horses. Mural
painting by John Fuchamp. Logging in the
main woods.
So cool to see that at a post office,
right? They still keep it.
Yeah, it really is such a hodge podge
here. And then we have a gallery sort of
standing out.
That smells so good. The smell of wood.
>> How you doing? Are these all made
locally?
>> We make everything locally here. Yes. No
way.
>> For reclaimed wood that we recover from
Quakeish Lake that's been underwater for
over 100 years. The majority of it is
4ft pulp wood that was destined for the
paper mill. We know the tree length was
cut in 1899 because that's when they
made a man-made lake where all of this
sits.
>> I do have a local carpenter.
>> You got a local carpenter doing this?
>> And our main product is our timber sheet
product. So this is an eighth of an inch
thick with double-sided tape on the
back. I think I bought some of this.
>> Really?
>> Or a competitor of yours.
>> There's a there's a
>> I put I put that on a wall of mine. That
stuff's awesome.
>> Well, I hope it was us.
>> Yeah, me too.
>> I got on Amazon.
>> Um, we sell on Amazon. We have our
>> I think it No, it is. It is you guys. I
see the brand.
>> Okay.
>> Yes. So, I put this on a wall. What one
did I have? It was more like It was this
one. It was exactly this one.
>> Yep. So, I had a wall and it was just
sort of a boring room and so it was like
for an accent wall
>> just to give it some
>> some texture and color.
>> You know, you sell the stuff
>> now. I'm selling it for you.
>> So, uh
>> but Okay. So, in this town, how does it,
if you don't mind, I get it now. Like,
you can sell this outside of town cuz I
was like, how are you going to sell this
table in town and make a living off
that?
>> That's what this product is for.
>> Exactly. Okay. We can't ship that. So
that it's really just people coming in
off the streets. And the only time we
get people off the streets is during the
summer.
>> And these are second homeowners that are
buying this stuff, right?
>> Yeah. I mean campers around here.
>> Camp owners. Okay. You getting a lot of
those people out here?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. So they have a camp. They come up
for the summer.
>> They're seasonal.
>> Seasonal. Okay. Did you grow up here?
>> I did.
>> How was it?
>> Born and raised. It was a lot better
back then than it is now. But but I have
a couple of kids and I still, you know,
I want to be here.
>> Okay. So, the mill went out in ' 08.
>> Mhm.
>> You're not that old. So, you saw that
downturn.
>> I actually worked in the mill for um a
couple years. I did accounting in the
mill. I'm I'm almost 40, so I love
>> Oh, okay. Well, good for you. Um Okay.
So, you saw that whole transition.
>> I did.
>> Was that rough?
>> Yeah. Yeah, it was.
>> I was with Dick and Gotti.
>> Yep. today. You know Dick?
>> I do.
>> So he cruised me around the mill.
>> Y
>> and told me about the history.
>> Okay.
>> And he was very much into the mill. Like
it was everything. He he he looks Okay.
So they have a real positive reputation
then?
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> So you're saying there's no replacement
yet?
>> No. Not. I mean the mill brought in
hundreds of jobs. We don't have anything
that's replaced that year. We employ
about 20 people y here and I think we're
probably the third or fourth biggest
company in the area.
>> Well, thank you.
>> Yeah, absolutely. My name's Jamie.
>> Jamie. And people should they buy from
you or Amazon?
>> Go right to us.
>> All right.
>> Thank you.
>> Thank you. I always like to promote
small businesses doing cool things.
>> How you doing, sir? Good. How are you
doing,
>> sir? Are you from Milaninoet?
>> Yes, I am.
>> How are things going?
>> Good.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Well, for me it is.
>> You're an electrician. What are you
doing?
>> Yes, I am.
>> Is your name Sparky?
>> Uh, yes it is.
>> It is.
>> No, it's Joe. Joe's electric.
>> Okay.
>> I live right up here.
>> Okay. Did you work in the mill back in
the day?
>> I did.
>> What was that like when it went out of
business?
>> Uh, well, I went to college at 48 years
old.
>> Wow.
>> Yes. Honest. And then uh I was lucky
enough they paid for everything because
I was um actually a laidoff worker. So
the state paid for my schooling.
>> Okay. So you got laid off and you're
like okay I got to come up with plan B.
>> Shut down.
>> It shut down. Yeah. It shut down and
then you're like plan B I got to go to
college.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Well I had to do something.
I was only 48 years old, so I had to do
something and I picked the electrical
field and so I did good and uh yeah
because u I've been you know doing well
ever since.
>> That's awesome.
>> And it was paid for. They sent me to
college and then I got home and I went
to work and ended up getting my license
which was hard.
>> People don't know you're going to have
schooling be an electrician.
>> Yeah.
>> They they don't realize that.
>> What's the name of your business? Joe's
>> door electric.
>> But everyone knows you in town, don't
they?
>> Oh yeah. Are you the only guy?
>> Well, it's two, three of us.
>> How's the town right now? What do you
think?
>> Uh, well, I I I don't know. I I do a lot
of work. Uh, not a lot of stuff lot of
stuff happening up the lakes.
>> The summer camps.
>> Yeah. Yeah. A lot of stuff happening up
here in town, too, though.
>> I work for one fell. He owns uh both
trailer parks here in East Monrok
and other trailer parks along with all
the houses he bought. So, some guy came
in here, bought a ton of houses.
>> Well, yes, he did. He's got an
investment group that works with that
>> investment group.
>> Yeah. So, yeah.
>> What are what are they doing with them?
You know,
>> it's a bunch of guys that, you know, got
together and said, "We think we're
supposed to do something."
And so, they come up here and uh they
bought a bunch of property and they fix
them up and they house people or sell
them.
>> Are people moving to town?
>> Uh, well, not really. There's only so
much uh you know place to move in this
town.
>> They're not building. You're not
building.
>> Nothing new.
>> Nothing. No. No. Nothing new. They're
trying to keep the other old stuff.
>> That's what this is. The
>> Are these the hikers that are hiking the
Appalachian Trail?
>> I don't know that.
>> I think they look like hikers.
>> Might be.
>> But that's a thing here too, right?
>> Oh, yeah. Big time.
>> Big time. Okay.
>> Yes, it is. No. Yeah. There's a lot of h
lot of things happening in Lowenov.
>> I love it, Joe.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Peter Santinelo.
>> Okay.
>> Nice to meet you.
>> Nice to meet you, too, though.
>> All right. If anyone needs work, Joe's
electric.
>> No, no, no. I don't go.
>> You're You're good on work. Okay. Never
mind.
>> See that, though?
>> See you, Joe.
>> All the best.
All
right, coming up to the end of
commercial Milaninoet. All these
restaurants are closed. Saloon the same.
Or maybe that's open. See fans in the
window. See who we can find.
>> How you doing? What's your name?
>> Yeah.
>> Andrew. You're the boss man here,
>> I guess. Something like that.
>> Peter.
>> Peter. Nice to meet you.
>> And you just saw me on the street like a
weirdo talking to my camera.
>> I saw you walking down in the middle of
Main Street holding this thing up and
then some van stopped you.
>> Joe's electric.
>> And I was like, what is he doing?
Like
>> what? But the bigger question is, what's
going on in here? This is a funky place.
>> Yeah. My father built this bar. He
bought this building back in ' 88 and
took 6 years. cuz it was a condemned
building and he rebuilt everything. This
wasn't a bar before. Everything you see
in here, my was my father's.
>> No way.
>> Yeah. Love child.
>> Did he work in the mill?
>> Uh when he first moved here, he moved
here in 71.
>> Okay.
>> Yeah. A little bit after uh he got out
of Vietnam, moved here. He grew up in
Platsburg, moved here, fell in love with
the town, and worked in the mill I think
maybe 6 months or something like that.
But he's had multiple businesses here.
He used to have a pizza shop. um a
couple other things till he finally
opened this up in
>> 1994 and he's been open every day since.
>> Whose idea was all this? Your dad's.
>> Oh, yeah. Everything in this is my
father's brainchild.
of his eccentricity. I guess that's one
of the Indians I think from outside the
old tobacco shops and stuff. You see
it's like solid mahogany
>> skates canoe.
>> This these are old town canoes. I think
this was from the late 1800s.
This over here was like the first
electric cash register. I think around
1915.
>> The bear with the bra.
>> Yeah. Actually, a girl came in here the
other night and said that's my bar from
like 6 years ago. That was the original
cash reg when he opened the bar up.
>> Oh, that's so cool.
>> Old national. We still have
>> everything still. We're an analog
stronghold in a digital world. No credit
cards here.
>> Only cash.
>> Yeah. Old school register.
>> Accept credit card in that.
>> Loving it. This is a sign my father had
hanging outside out in front of the
building
>> uh while he was building it. Coming soon
the blue saloon. Free beer tomorrow.
>> So is this place get busy?
>> Yeah.
>> Well, when the mill was here it was over
what 5,000 people. So it was a way
different town like when my father
opened this up. When he opened up there
was seven bars on this street.
>> Do you Okay. How old How old are you?
>> I'm I'll be 44 next month.
>> Okay. So you remember when the mill was
happening here? So, I grew I didn't grow
I was born here. Didn't grow up here.
I'd come and visit my father and stuff.
But yeah, like I mean you when like back
when he opened this in the '9s, there
was a line out front the door like you
had a you had a bouncer. There was you
couldn't you couldn't get in.
>> Wow.
>> The back room used to be opened up but
it's since
>> and now you got an outdoors.
>> The old Gordon Fisherman.
>> So even though the business is so much
down because of the mill, your dad still
wanted to keep it open.
>> Yeah. I'll never give up. He told me it
was always since I was a kid. They said,
"You never sell this place."
>> What's your take on the town right now?
Where it's at, 2026. Where do you see it
going?
>> I think everything comes in cycles right
now. We're in that difficult transition.
I think also the the average age in this
town is 60. So, the predominant serious
>> So, yeah, it's a much older generation.
is a generation of people that have held
on that
uh
so I
>> so I moved back here 2 years ago.
>> Okay. tell my father.
I'd say that the people that were in
this town, at least from what I've
witnessed, like from my father's
perspective, is they never would have
seen how the decline happened.
>> Mhm.
>> And so you asked about the bar staying
open, like my father would never ever
quit. This man
>> Yeah. a two tour Vietnam vet. Like he
would be here right now, but he ruptured
some discs two months ago. Just had back
surgery, so he's been a bit out, but
he's almost 80 and he's here 7 days a
week. Like,
>> okay.
>> Always going. Um he's always believed in
this town. At one point, he had
purchased one of the buildings over here
to put the uh museum here on downtown,
but then they ended up rerouting and
things happened. Um he still has the
blueprints downstairs somewhere. I was I
saw him the other day. But so this town,
what I recognized in is I feel like
everything in this town was about the
mill. This town started because of it.
1898 I think the mills started. 191 the
town was established and it grew because
of the mill. And so this entire town
when that all stopped, it's it's there's
a there's a grieving, you know, it's the
it's the loss of a dream, a loss of a a
life unlived. Because I think if you
looked at this town from when the mills
were open, no one could have anticipated
this happening,
>> right?
>> Like no one would have seen
the way that the the internet is like
and just paper just disappeared. I mean
they made all the At one point this was
the largest paper mill in the world.
>> No way. I didn't even know that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Even though I see this
sense of grief that's going through this
is a town of very resilient people. Some
of the heartier Americans you're going
to find.
>> Everyone I've talked to is super cool.
>> Yeah. And I think that there will be,
you know, just like I was saying before,
the cycles like there there's young
energy coming in. They're redoing some
areas downtown. Everything could always
be better and faster. And I guess the
goal is like how do I with taking on
what my father has continue in doing
some of the things for this town that he
wanted to see done. He always wanted
trees planted down along this to have it
really inviting. He was one of the he
was the first person to have a
handcarved sign just to make it like
really quaint. like you had a lot of
ideas that were really beautiful for
this town and it's definitely uh
>> some big shoes to fill, but like I I I
see a revival here and and he's given me
this this landmark to be a part of that.
And
>> you going to stay out?
>> Yeah. There's something magical about
this place. I mean, Mount Kataden, it's
the first place in North America during
this time of year to get light
>> right there at the peak. Yeah.
>> No way. And you know what I love is just
the buffer zone
>> because to get here it takes a long
time. There's no way around that.
>> Yeah.
>> There's not like a big town next door.
Not a big town over there.
>> I mean the gateway to the northern
woods.
>> It even gives more. Huh.
>> Yes. The northern woods.
>> Yeah. It's cool.
>> Well, keep it up, bro.
>> Yeah.
>> And I'm going to send people your way.
Blue a saloon.
>> I appreciate it.
>> For a good cold one.
>> Yeah.
>> You make good mixed drinks, too. Or
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> The full monty.
He's been hiking already.
>> This guy, how many days you been hiking?
>> Uh, we did five. So, not that long.
>> You can start here and end in Georgia,
right?
>> Yeah. Spring Mountain.
>> That's what you guys are going to do.
>> That's what we're going to do.
>> How long?
>> 5 months. November 22nd.
>> How you feeling about it?
>> You know, excited.
>> Can't do nothing now but do it and plan
for it. So, we just got
>> That's wild. Five months.
>> Yeah.
>> In a tent with a backpack.
>> Yeah. Yeah, you go through towns like
stay in some places like this.
>> What do you guys think of this place?
>> Pretty sweet.
>> He's sleeping in that bus over there.
>> Yeah.
>> What's this bus?
>> It's a Yeah, they made like a bus for
like people that have dogs or something
like that. So, like look inside of it, I
guess.
>> Oh, yeah. Let's check it out.
>> I have my dog so she can't stay in the
community bunk. So, they gave us this
little private bus to stay in for two
nights.
>> This is for you and your dog?
>> Yeah.
>> Nice. You and
>> the pup.
>> This is sweet. Can I go in?
>> Yeah. Yeah, for sure. All right.
This is cool. All set up. Well,
>> that's my crib.
>> Yeah, dude.
>> It's your crib. Van life.
>> It's where the magic happens, you know?
Like,
>> so we're best friends from St. Louis,
Missouri. Like, we went to high school
together there.
>> Oh, nice.
>> Now, we live different places. Like, he
lives in North Carolina now and I live
in Maryland. So, we met at one time to
go cabin
>> camping in Shannondoa and then we were
like, let's just do the ET. Just commit
to it. That's that's a bold commitment.
>> Your work is cool with it or you just
have to change jobs? My work's cool with
it.
>> My work gave me a six-mon sbatical
>> to go and come back.
>> What do you What do you hope to
accomplish out of that or like what do
you think you'll get out of it?
>> Peace. I mean, like, you know, we always
get with going with work and everything,
we get caught up in our routine and
everything. It'd be nice to kind of like
disconnect, get away from like the news,
be out in nature, be like present in
like every day.
Yeah, I I work on software development,
so I'm always on the computer. Just like
disconnect for a while, probably break
break down and then hopefully build back
stronger.
And that's Milanino. Interesting past,
unknown future. Great people we met
today. I like this town. It's been a
short time here, but there's just
something about its simplicity and its
story, and it'll be interesting to come
back in 10 years or so to see where it
goes. This is part of a greater main
series. Have other videos from the
state. Shooting one more. There'll be
five in total. And then the book is now
live.
Got that link down here around here. For
most people in the country, you can
order it now and get it tomorrow. Your
fellow Americans, thanks for coming
along on that journey. Until the next
one.